Hello, everyone.
大家好
I hope you're having a fantastic time at this event.
我希望你们在这次大会中度过一段美好的时光
I'm very sorry, I can't be there with you,
我很抱歉 我不能和你们在一起
but i'm hoping to join you sometime in the near future.
但我希望在不久的将来能加入到你们之中
I am rebecca rumble,
我是瑞贝卡·朗布尔
I am the executive director and ceo of the Rust foundation.
Rust 基金会的执行董事兼首席执行官
I'd like to talk to you a little bit today about how Rust is for everyone
今天
and how the Rust foundation is looking to
我想和大家谈谈 Rust 是如何为每个人服务的
support maintainers and developers of the language in china and around the world.
以及 Rust 基金会是如何支持中国和世界各地的语言维护者和开发者的
A little bit about the Rust foundation,
关于 Rust 基金会
we are an independent non-profit organization,
我们是一个独立的非营利组织
and our role is to steward the Rust programming language and ecosystem.
我们的角色是管理 Rust 编程语言和生态系统
What that means is that we want to support,
这意味着我们希望支持
sustain and grow the Rust programming language.
维持和发展 Rust 编程语言
We want to do that globally through strategic investment,
我们希望在全球范围内通过战略投资
in developing the language,
通过开发语言
through virtual and in person collaboration,
通过线上和线下的合作
at events like these,
在这样的活动中
through training and education,
通过培训和教育
providing courses,
提供课程
and through promotional,
以及通过推广
collaborative governance and technical infrastructure,
协作治理和技术基础设施
we want the Rust language to be as good as it can possibly be,
从而使 Rust 语言尽可能好
so that the users can have as much fun and work with it as possible.
以便用户可以尽可能多地享受乐趣并使用它
I'm sure I don't need to tell any of you
我相信我不需要告诉你们任何关于 Rust 编程语言的事情
about the RUST programming language and how amazing it is.
以及它有多么神奇
Just a kind of little summary.
总结来说
Rust is really fast.
Rust 很快
It's a memory safe and memory efficient language.
它是一种内存安全和内存高效的语言
One of the great features is that it has no run time and no garbage collector,
其中一个很棒的特性是 它没有运行时 也没有垃圾回收器
and it can power performance,
并且它可以为性能
critical services.
和关键服务提供动力
It can run on embedded devices.
它可以在嵌入式设备上运行
It can easily integrate with other languages.
它可以很容易地与其他语言集成
Rust also has great documentation.
Rust 也有很好的文档
It's got a friendly compiler with useful error messages,
它有一个友好的编译器，提供实用的错误信息
and its got top notch tooling,
并且配备了一流的工具链
an integrated package manager build tool.
一个集成的包管理器构建工具
It's got a lot of support type inspections or to format and more.
它有很多支持类型检查或格式化等
I hope that you will love using the Rust language as much as we do.
我希望你能像我们一样喜欢使用 Rust 语言
I'd like to say that I am
我想说的是
so delighted at how RUST is being adopted and used in china.
我对 Rust 在中国被采用和使用的方式感到非常高兴
I love the fact that so many developers are discovering
我很高兴有这么多开发人员发现了这种奇妙的语言
this wonderful language and joining our international community.
并加入了我们的国际社区
It's great to see Rust increasingly being used by companies in china,
很高兴看到中国的公司越来越多地使用 Rust
such as Huawei Bytedance and Weibo.
比如华为,字节跳动和微博 （还有蚂蚁集团、非凸科技、在线途游等）
I really delighted to see that the educational system is also taking notice
我真的很高兴看到教育系统也注意到了 Rust
of Rust and providing
并为中国学生
good educational materials to students in china.
提供了良好的教育材料
Rust  textbooks are being written specifically for Chinese students,
Rust 教科书是专门为中国学生编写的
which is great to develop a good curriculum and a good grounding in RUST
这对于开发一个好的课程和为将来的编程打下一个好的 Rust 基础
for programming in the future.
是非常好的
I'm also really glad to see so many new meet ups for RUST are happening all
我也很高兴看到这么多新的关于 Rust 的meetups
over china.
在中国各地举行
I'm aware that so many are already happening in Shanghai,
我知道在上海 北京和其他地方已经发生了很多这样的事情
Beijing and elsewhere and id love to see those meet ups grow.
我很乐意看到这些事情的发展
And I think its also worth noting that the Chinese RUST community is
我认为同样值得注意的是
the third largest RUST community by country in the world.
中国 Rust 社区是世界上第三大 Rust 社区
6.09 of RUST users that responded to the annual RUST survey are from china.
填写年度 Rust 调查的RUST用户中有6.09%来自中国
Thats only behind the USA and Germany.
仅次于美国和德国
So thats more users than the UK or the Netherlands.
所以这比英国或荷兰的用户还多
And that's really great.
这真的很棒
It's so great to see so many developers in china using RUST productively
很高兴看到中国有这么多开发人员高效地使用 Rust
and Rust is growing.
Rust 也在增长
This is good news.
这是个好消息
Rust.
Rust 的
Adoption is growing rapidly.
采用率正在迅速增长
Global users are troubling in the last 3 years to 2.5 million.
在过去的 3 年里 全球用户数量达到了 250万
And I should say that some of these figures are a little bit out of date.
我要说的是 其中一些数字有点已经过时了
Now.
现在
So I think that 2.5 million is actually more like 3 or 3.5 million at this point.
所以我认为 250 万实际上更像是 300 万或 350 万
RUST is also the most loved language amongst developers for the past 6 years.
在过去的 6 年里 Rust 也是开发人员最喜爱的语言
That is incredible.
太不可思议了
So many developers that come to Rust,
如此多的开发人员使用 Rust
really grow to love using it.
真正成长为喜欢使用它
For the first time last year,
去年
Rust was also voted most wanted language amongst developers.
Rust 还首次被选为开发人员最想要的语言
That is really significant because it demonstrates that not only do people
这是非常重要的 因为它表明不仅人们
love Rust,
喜欢 Rust
but companies are desperate to have good proficient RUST programmers
而且公司也迫切希望拥有优秀 Rust 技术的程序员作为
as part of their staff.
其员工的一部分
The great thing about RUST and its memory safety features is that it's now
Rust 及其内存安全功能的伟大之处在于
being cited as a key security solution.
它现在被认为是一种关键的安全解决方案
For open source,
对于开源来说
it's really important as part of supply chain security initiatives,
它作为供应链安全计划的一部分非常重要
because it avoids a lot of the memory issues that are associated
因为它避免了许多与 C++ 等语言
with languages like c plus.
相关的内存问题
We have a vision for us at the foundation.
我们在基金会有一个愿景
It's our job to make sure that us continues to grow,
我们的工作是确保我们继续成长
continues to be useful and continues to be productive.
继续有用 继续富有成效
We want us to be considered a universally safe,
我们希望我们被认为是一种普遍安全
secure and sustainable language.
可靠和可持续的语言
We want it to be tRUSTed by individual developers,
我们希望它能得到个人开发者
by organizations and by governments.
组织和政府的信任
We want to make sure that RUST is maintained by a resource,
我们希望确保 Rust 由资源支持
supported, inclusive and diverse global community.
包容和多样化的全球社区维持
We don't just want RUST developers from the us or from europe.
我们不只是想要来自美国或欧洲的 Rust 开发人员
We want to embrace people all over the world to use RUST.
我们希望拥抱世界各地的人们使用 Rust
As i've said,
正如我所说的
Rust adoption continues to grow,
Rust 的采用率继续增长
and we want to see that trajectory continue.
我们希望看到这一轨迹继续下去
We want it to become the go to language for its security and memory safety features.
我们希望它因其安全性和内存安全功能而成为热门语言
We want to know that the companies that benefit most from RUST,
我们想知道的是 从 Rust 中受益最大的公司
become and continue to be active investors and stakeholders in its future growth.
将成为并继续成为其未来增长的积极投资者和利益相关者
We want those companies to join the foundation to help govern how we
我们希望这些公司加入基金会
develop the language.
帮助管理我们开发语言的方式
And we want to invest in Rust education,
我们希望投资于 Rust 教育
we want to develop training and we want to increase opportunities
我们希望发展培训以及
and growth in use and adoption.
增加使用和接纳的机会
Some of the ways we're investing in Rust through a security initiative,
我们通过安全计划对 Rust 进行投资的一些方式
which is helping to secure the RUST ecosystem.
有助于保护 Rust 生态系统
That means were ensuring that your software is secure,
这意味着我们确保您的软件是安全的
were trying to automate tooling and features in the RUST ecosystem,
我们尝试在 Rust 生态系统中自动化工具和功能
so that you are not victims of typo squatting,
这样您就不会被打字错误所困扰
that the crates are not vulnerable to attack,
代码库不容易受到攻击
and that your software can be used all around the world.
并且您的软件可以在世界各地使用
We have a RUST to c plus inter operation initiative that
我们有一个 Rust 到 C++ 的交互操作计划
is working to help bridge the gap between RUST and C++,
该计划正在帮助弥合 Rust 和 C++ 之间的差距
because we want to ensure that companies that have a lot
因为我们希望确保拥有大量 C++
of legacy C++ code can still use Rust to make that code safer.
代码的公司仍然可以使用 Rust 来使代码更安全
We want to make sure that, look,
我们想要确保
those companies that would like to move to Rust,
那些想要转移到 Rust
but can't rewrite everything,
但不能重写一切的公司
can still use the memory safety features.
仍然可以使用内存安全功能
We have developed this year a safety critical consortium,
我们今年成立了一个安全关键联盟
which is working to bring together the safety critical industry to ensure
致力于将安全关键行业聚集在一起
that Rust is fit for purpose.
以确保 Rust 符合目的
If any of you are working in a safety critical industry
如果你们中的任何人在安全关键行业工作
and would like to join that consortium,
并希望加入该联盟
please look at our website.
请查看我们的网站
We'd be delighted to have you join that consortium and share your views
我们很高兴您能加入该联盟
with us were also working on a Rust
并与我们分享您的观点
specification to provide basic and universal RUST back to enable people to program
我们还在制定 Rust 规范 以提供基本和通用的 Rust
the same all over the world.
使人们能够在世界各地进行相同的编程
We have a community grants program,
我们有一个社区资助计划
which helps maintainers work on the projects that they love.
帮助维护人员在他们喜欢的项目上工作
The community grants program provides grants for events,
社区补助金计划为一年中持续
for travel and for fellowships that last between 6 months in a year,
6个月的活动
a lot of those grants make sure that individuals can work on areas
旅行和奖学金提供补助金 其中很多补助金确保个人可以在他们真正
of the RUST project that they really love,
喜欢和感兴趣的 Rust
and they're really interested in.
项目领域工作
And that will help the Rust community overall.
这将有助于整个 Rust 社区
And we have a Rust education initiative where we are developing
我们有一个 Rust 教育计划 我们正在为想要学习 Rust
official RUST courses online for developers,
或想要学习嵌入式等特定内容的
wanting to learn RUST or wanting to learn specific things like embedded.
开发人员开发正式的在线 Rust 课程
Or I think.
或者我认为
So looking to the future,
从未来的角度考虑
Rust numbers are growing all the time.
Rust 的数量一直在增长
There's billions of crates that I have downloads every year.
我每年都会下载数十亿个库
As I said,
正如我所说 我们正在调查
we're investigating but investigating new initiatives to support and grow
新的倡议
the Rust community all the time.
以支持和发展 Rust 社区
If any of you have ideas about what you think the Rust foundation
如果你们中的任何人对 Rust 基金会应该如何发展
should be doing to develop Rust,
Rust 有任何想法
please get in touch with us.
请与我们联系
We're also working with governments around the world to promote RUSTs,
我们还与世界各地的政府合作 促进 Rust
features and memory safety.
特性和内存安全
This is really important.
这真的很重要
Governments have a lot of sway over what kind of code should be used
政府对应该使用哪种代码来确保供应链安全
to secure the supply chain.
有很大的影响力
We're working closely with those governments to ensure they understand what
我们正在与这些政府密切合作
RUST can provide.
以确保他们了解 Rust 可以提供什么
We're also hoping to work with more and more companies in china and asia
我们也希望与中国和亚洲地区越来越多的公司
area.
合作
We want to understand what your needs are for adoption.
我们希望了解您对融入 Rust 的需求
We want to understand how we can help make adoption easier and more smooth
我们希望了解如何帮助您更轻松
for you.
更顺利地采用
We hope to partner with chinese organizations in 2025 to contribute to events,
我们希望在2025年与中国组织合作
because we would love to come and see you all and meet you all.
为活动做出贡献 因为我们很乐意与你们见面
So please, my main message here is get involved.
所以我的想法是请大家参与进来
First is growing.
首先是成长
It's really exciting faith,
这是非常令人兴奋的信仰
and we would love to have you join us in one or another way.
我们希望你能以某种方式加入我们
We definitely need more maintainers on the Rust project.
Rust 项目确实需要更多的维护人员
There is a Rust zulip chat,
有一个 Rust zulip Chat
which can enable you to talk directly with the leadership and perhaps join
它可以让你直接与领导层交谈
some of the project teams.
也许还可以加入一些项目团队
We would love you to contribute to the leadership of the Rust project.
我们希望您能为 Rust 项目的领导做出贡献
Sign up to this weekend Rust.
报名参加这个周末的 Rust
That is a great mailing list that tells you what's going on in RUST all
这是一个很棒的邮件列表
over the world.
它告诉您世界各地的 Rust 正在发生什么
It provides information on the latest rfcs and provides opportunities
它提供了有关最新 RFC 的信息
for developers to get involved.
并为开发人员提供了参与机会
We would love to have more chinese companies join the Rust foundation as members.
我们希望有更多的中国公司加入 Rust 基金会
Our members shape our strategy and our investment approach and they
我们的成员塑造我们的战略和投资方法
influence how we do things.
他们影响我们做事的方式
Having more chinese members as part of the foundation will enable asia
让更多的中国成员成为基金会的一部分
to have a much more prominent voice in the work we do and how we
将使亚洲在我们所做的工作和我们的治理方式中拥有更突出的
are governed.
发言权
So thank you all for listening.
谢谢大家的聆听
I hope you all have a fantastic event,
我希望你们都有一个精彩的大会
and I hope to be there next year to meet you all in person.
我希望明年能亲自去那里与你们见面
Thank you very much.
非常感谢